Guide to the Maurice Hewlett Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Maurice Hewlett collection
1892-1930
GEN MSS 60
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1
(3 boxes) + 1 portfolio
Collection contains letters by Maurice Hewlett to various recipients, including Sir John Collings Squire, and some third party correspondence. Also in the collection are holograph and typescript writings by Hewlett including his Song of the Plow, an obituary of Hewlett and a collotype of Hewlett by Alvin Langdon Coburn.
Hewlett, Maurice, 1861-1923
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ongoing collection of documents acquired by gift and purchase from various sources. Source information is recorded on the folders. For further information, consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Portfolio: Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
MAURICE HEWLETT (1861-1923)
Maurice Hewlett was born in Weybridge, Surrey, England on 22 January 1861, the oldest child of Henry G. Hewlett, the keeper of the royal land revenue records, and Emmeline Mary Knowles Hewlett. Hewlett attended school at the Sevenoaks grammar school, Palace School in Enfield, and International College in Spring Grove, Isleworth. He joined his cousin's law office in 1878, and in 1888 married Hilda Beatrice Herbert, with whom he had two children. He succeeded his father in the post of keeper of land revenue records from 1897 until 1900.
In 1898 Hewlett published The Forest Lovers, which brought him wide renown. He dedicated the rest of his life to his writing, publishing historical fiction, poetry, essays and plays. His more widely known works include Earthwork out of Tuscany (1895), The Life of Richard Yea-and-Nay (1900), and The Song of the Plow (1916). Hewlett died in 1923.
Scope and Contents
This finding aid encompasses accessions of single manuscripts and small groups of manuscripts and other papers, by or pertaining to Maurice Hewlett, acquired by the library from a variety of sources. Materials incorporated into the collection prior to May 1999 have been organized into four series. Series I, Charles Parsons Gift (1892-1930), includes letters from Hewlett to Sir John Collings Squire and others, third party correspondence, and writings of Hewlett. Series II, Philip Neufeld Gift (1896-1916), contains letters from Hewlett, and writings of Hewlett including drafts of his Song of the Plow. Series III, Bertram Rota Purchase (1909-1923), contains letters and writings by Hewlett. Series IV, Materials from Other Sources (1912-1923), contains letters from Hewlett.
Authors, English -- 20th Century; Novelists, English -- 20th Century; Poets, English -- 20th Century; Authors; Novelists; Poets; The Song of the Plow; Coburn, Alvin Langdon, 1882-1966; Hewlett, Maurice, 1861-1923; Squire, John Collings, Sir, 1884-1958
- Charles Parsons Gift, 1892-1930; Series I; 0.4; (1 box)
  Scope and Contents
  Gift of Charles Parsons, 1939 and 1944
  - CORRESPONDENCE
    - Letters from Maurice Henry Hewlett
      - Campbell, Mrs. Patrick, 1920 Aug 1
        Related Archival Materials note
        See: Writings, "The Queen of Scots," Box 1, folder 18
      - Chambers, Mr.
        See: Third Party Letters, Bertram Rota to Mrs. Parsons, Box 1, folder 15
      - Colles, William Morris, 1909-12 (Box 1, Folder 1)
        Letter of 1912 Oct 23 removed from Hewlett's "Lore of Proserpine..."
      - Mathews, Elkin, 1909, 1910 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Squire, John Collings, Sir, 1915-23, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 3-8)
      - Thorley, Salisbury, 1911 Nov 11 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - ----, Norman, [n.y.] May 13 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Unidentified, 1909, 1910, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Third Party Letters
      - Bernard Quaritch (Firm) to Charles Parsons
        See: Bertram Rota to Mrs. Parsons, Box 1, folder 15
      - Hewlett, William to Charles Parsons, 1929-30 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Judge, Max to Mr. Muir, 1929 Sep 16 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - Poole, Reginald Stuart to C. Shorter, 1892 Dec 15 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - Rota, Bertram to Mrs. Parsons, 1930 Jun 14 (Box 1, Folder 15)
        Includes: Letter from MH to Mr. Chambers, 1 Dec [1909?], and letter from Bernard Quaritch (Firm) to Charles Parsons, 26 May 1930, referring to Hewlett's "Earthwork out of Tuscany"
      - Welby-Everard, Mrs. Gay M. P. to Charles Parsons, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 16)
        Writing to Mr. Parsons as literary executrix of Maurice Hewlett's books and manuscripts
        Includes: Holograph of Hewlett's monthly review of books for the London Mercury, "Biography and Mirrors," and two bookplates of Hewlett's
  - WRITINGS OF MAURICE HENRY HEWLETT
    - The Birth of Roland, typescript (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - "The Queen of Scots," typescript play, corrected, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 18-20)
      Includes: Letter from Hewlett to Mrs. Patrick Campbell, 1 Aug 1920
  - OTHER PAPERS
    - Squire, Sir John Collings. Obituary of Maurice Hewlett, clipping of printed version from "The Observer", 1923 Jun 17 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Coburn, Alvin Langdon. Collotype of Hewlett, reproduction (2 copies), 1914 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Philip M. Neufeld Gift, 1896-1916; Series II; 0.4; (1 box)
  Gift of Philip M. and Margaret Neufeld, 1953-1965
  - LETTERS FROM MAURICE HEWLETT
    - "Gilder", [n.y.] Sep 9 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Salter, Mr., 1916 Jun 16 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - WRITINGS
    - Song of the Plow
      - "Books 1 - 6," holograph, corrected, 1913 Nov 19 (Box 2, Folder 25-28)
      - "Books 1 - 11," holograph, corrected, 1915 Jan 25 (Box 2, Folder 29-35)
      - Holograph, corrected, [ca. 1916?] (Box 2, Folder 36-47)
    - Other Writings
      - "An Armenian Knight's Entertainment," typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 48)
      - "Jacob's Ladder," holograph poem (Box 2, Folder 49)
      - Pan and the Young Shepherd, holograph play, 1896 Jan 4 (Box 2, Folder 50-52)
        Includes: Two sketches for the cover of the book, published by John Lane in 1898
- Purchases from Bertram Rota Ltd., 1909-1923; Series III; 0.1; (.5 box)
  Purchased from Bertram Rota on the Library Associates Fund, Starling W. Childs Fund, Frederick W. Hilles Fund, Ernest F. Hodgdon Fund, Hubert Amer McGuire Memorial Fund, John Ewing Durand Memorial Fund, and Beinecke Funds, 1960-1978
  - LETTERS FROM MAURICE HENRY HEWLETT
    - Ionides, Basil, 1912-13 (Box 3, Folder 53)
    - Mathews, Elkin, [1909?] May 12 (Box 3, Folder 54)
    - Smith, Mrs. Graham, 1923 (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - WRITINGS BY MAURICE HENRY HEWLETT
    - "The Invitation to Wiltshire," typescript, corrected, ca. 1923 (Box 3, Folder 56)
    - "The Silence of the Village," typescript, corrected, ca. 1923 (Box 3, Folder 57)
- Materials from Other Sources, 1912-1923; Series IV; 0.1; (.5 box)
  Acquired by gift or purchase from various sources, as indicated on individual folders
  - LETTERS FROM MAURICE HENRY HEWLETT
    - Cagluone, C. F., 1913 Oct 22 (Box 3, Folder 58)
      Includes: Clippings of 3 reviews of novels by MH
    - Haddon, Trevor, 1919 Apr 4 (Box 3, Folder 59)
    - Ionides, Basil, 1912 Apr 9 (Box 3, Folder 60)
    - Judge, Max, [n.y.] May 5 (Box 3, Folder 61)
    - Thorley, Wilfred Charles, 1923, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 62)
    - Varney, G. L., [n.y.] Oct 18 (Box 3, Folder 63)
- Restricted Fragile
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Box 1, folder 21 (Box Portfolio, Folder 64)
  - Box 2, folder 36 (Box Portfolio, Folder 65)
  - Box 2, folder 38 (Box Portfolio, Folder 66)
  - Box 3, folder 58 (Box Portfolio, Folder 67)